Guide to the Joyce Matz Papers 1969-2017 MS 3050
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Historic Preservation and quality of life issues, 1971-2013; 227676; 17 Linear feet
  - Community Coalition | East 76th Street Rezoning [2 folders], 1999-2000; 224982 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 9-10)
    In 1999 the developer of a large site at 506 East 76th Street applied to have the property rezoned from manufacturing to residential, hoping to capitalize on its maximum 31-story building potential. The City Planning Commission reduced the allowable height to 13 stories, which the community argued still exceeded an 8-story limit set in 1985 for all midblock areas of the Upper East Side.
  - Concerned Tenants of 823 Park Avenue [2 folders], 1992-1998; 224994 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 11-12)
    The City of New York seized the apartment building at 823 Park Avenue for non-payment of taxes, and sold it to Robert Manocherian in 1994. Matz's files document Manocherian's efforts to evict the tenants.
  - Convent of the Little Sisters of the Assumption / PLACE, 1984-1985; 224188 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 13)
    Documentation of the unsuccessful attempt by PLACE (Preserve the Landmarks and Character of the East Eighties) to landmark the Convent of the Little Sisters of the Assumption (originally the Convent of the Sisters of Bon Secours). The four-story, red-brick, Victorian Gothic structure at 1195 Lexington Avenue, was designed by architect William Schickel and built in 1889. It has since been demolished.
  - Coogan Building (Save the Coogan Coalition), 1999; 224390 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1)
    The 1876 Coogan Building, originally the Racket Court Club, at 776 Avenue of the Americas, was designed in the Romanesque Revival style by Alfred H. Thorp. It had its 1989 landmark designation overturned by the Board of Estimate. The efforts of a coalition formed to seek re-designation in 1999 were unsuccessful, and the building has since been replaced by a residential tower. The new structure does not appear to incorporate any of the Coogan's facade elements, despite promises from the developer that it would.
  - Defenders of the Historic Upper East Side [2 folders], 2000-2004; 224499 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2-3)
    A preservation advocacy group founded in 2003, Defenders of the Historic Upper East Side seeks to protect the historic character of Manhattan's Upper East Side from intrusive development.
  - Dry Cleaning Fumes [2 folders], 1994-2006; 226495 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4-5)
    Documentation of toxic tetrachloroethylene (a.k.a., perc) levels emitted by Fancy Cleaners, a dry cleaning business adjacent to 460 East 79th Street, where Joyce Matz occupied apartment 2B.
  - Dvorák Statue, 1993-1997; 224459 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 6)
    Fundraising efforts to restore and dedicate a statue of Czech composer Antonin Dvorák (1841-1904). The statue, by Croatian-American sculptor Ivan Mestrovic (1883-1962), had been presented to the New York Philharmonic in 1963. The Philharmonic donated it to the Dvorák American Heritage Association, which eventually placed it in Stuyvesant Square, nearly opposite the site of 327 East 17th Street, the house Dvorák occupied between 1892 and 1895 (demolished in 1991).
  - East 54th & East 55th Street Townhouses [6 folders], 1998-2001; 224981 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 7-12)
    Efforts to landmark townhouses on the north side of East 54th Street (nos. 111-121), south side of East 55th Street (nos. 116-124), and north side of East 55th Street (nos. 113-119). Ultimately, the New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission designated just two of the houses: no. 116-118 East 55th Street (the William and Helen Martin Murphy Ziegler, Jr. House) and no. 124 East 55th Street (the Mary Hale Cunningham House). For her work on this campaign, Matz received the Elliot Willensky Fund award for 2000 (see box 17, folder 8).
  - East 79th Street Block Association, 1986-1991; 227059 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 13)
    Press releases and newspaper clippings documenting the activities and concerns of the residents of a 24-block area of the Upper East Side anchored by East 79th Street between Third Avenue and the East River.
  - Ellis Island [3 folders], 1991-1992; 224983 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 14-16)
    Construction of a proposed conference center by the National Parks Service would have resulted in the demolition of several structures on Ellis Island. The New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission eventually created the Ellis Island Historic District to prohibit such changes.
  - Fire Patrol Stations, 2006; 224592 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1)
    Efforts to landmark Fire Patrol Station No. 1 (240 West 30th Street) and Fire Patrol Station No. 2 (84 West 3rd Street). Since 2013 the latter has been protected as part of the South Village Historic District.
  - Friends of Hudson River Park, 2006; 228006 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 2)
    Notes and press releases for Hudson River Park, the Manhattan greenway constructed along the Hudson River between West 59th Street and Battery Park beginning in the late 1990s.
  - Friends of the Upper East Side Historic Districts [3 folders], 1991-2000; 224453 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3-5)
    A not-for-profit membership group, Friends of the Upper East Side Historic Districts was founded in 1982 to maintain the architectural legacy and sense of place of the Upper East Side.
  - Grand Central Partnership, Inc., 1986-1988; 224284 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 6)
    Press releases and newspaper clippings outlining the proposed revitalization of Grand Central Terminal.
  - Gregory Towers Tenants' Coordinating Committee [3 folders], 1985-2000; 224458 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 7-9)
    Joyce Matz lived for many years in apartment 2B of the Gregory Towers, a 20-story building at 460 East 79th Street. Her files document the building's conversion from rental property to condominium, and the activities of the tenant's coordinating committee.
  - Guggenheim Neighbors: A Concerned Community Opposed to the Planned Addition to the Guggenheim Museum [7 folders], 1985-1992; 224984 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 10-16)
    Opposition to a proposed oversized addition to the Frank Lloyd Wright-designed Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, an exterior and interior landmark at 1071 Fifth Avenue.
  - Kaplan Fund, 1984; 224426 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 17)
    The J. M. Kaplan Fund, a philanthropic charity organized in 1945, supports varied causes, including heritage conservation.
  - Lake Minnewaska, Ulster County, New York, 1979-1980; 228220 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 18)
    Matz's typed reminiscence of her family's visits to Lake Minnewaska Mountain House in Ulster County, New York, submitted to the travel editor of the New York Times after the paper reported the resort had closed.
  - Lambs Club, 1999-2001; 224503 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 19)
    Information, clippings, and notes regarding the McKim, Mead & White-designed Lambs Club, an official New York City landmark at 128 West 44th Street.
  - Landmark West! The Committee to Preserve the Upper West Side [folder 1 of 4], 1987-2011; 224985 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 20)
    Press releases, newspaper clippings, brochures, and ephemera documenting the work of Landmark West!, a non-profit group organized in 1985 to achieve landmark status for individual buildings and historic districts on Manhattan's Upper West Side.
  - Landmark West! The Committee to Preserve the Upper West Side [folders 2-4 of 4], 1987-2011; 228363 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1-3)
  - Landmarks Lion Award [3 folders], 1999-2013; 224511 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 4-6)
    The Historic Districts Council named Joyce Matz its 2000 Landmarks Lion on 10 January 2001. The award has been presented since 1990 to individuals who show unusual devotion to historic districts and landmarks. Matz's files document her own award, as well as earlier and later recipients.
  - Lever House [2 folders], 1982-1983; 224236 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 7-8)
    Efforts to landmark and preserve Lever House, a glass and stainless steel-clad office building at 390 Park Avenue.
  - Madison Square North Historic District, 2001; 224387 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 9)
    Notes, correspondence, research, and testimony for the designation of the Madison Square North Historic District.
  - Memorial Sloan-Kettering expansion / 10021 Community Coalition [2 folders], 2001; 224987 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 10-11)
    Correspondence, research, press releases, and newspaper clippings on the opposition to Memorial Sloan-Kettering Hospital's plan for a 44-story tower on a mid-block site between First and York Avenues, East 68th and 69th Streets.
  - Metropolitan Club of New York, 1986-1987; 224988 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 12)
    Effort to block construction of a tower above the landmarked Metropolitan Club Building at 1-11 East 60th Street.
  - Moynihan Station, 2005-2006; 228007 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 13)
    Documentation of some of the early plans to redevelop the James A. Farley Building (the main U.S. Post Office for New York City) as a replacement for the vanished Pennsylvania Station. The facility, when complete, will be named for Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan (1927-2003), who championed the project.
  - Municipal Art Society / New York Coliseum [folders 1-3 of 11], 1987-1997; 224989 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 14-16)
    Press releases, newspaper clippings, and information regarding the Municipal Art Society's opposition to the replacement of the New York Coliseum, at Columbus Circle, by the complex that would eventually be known as the Time Warner Center.
  - Municipal Art Society / New York Coliseum [folders 4-11 of 11], 1987-1997; 228371 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1-8)
  - Neighbors R Us [folders 1-3 of 5], 1994-1997; 224990 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 9-11)
    Coalition of neighborhood groups against construction of a Toys R Us in a former warehouse at 1411 Third Avenue and 201 East 80th Street.
  - Neighbors R Us [folders 4-5 of 5], 1994-1997; 228372 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - New York City Landmarks Law, changes to, 1988-1989; 224394 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 3)
    Notes, press releases, and fliers documenting opposition to Mayor Edward Koch's proposed alterations to New York City's Landmarks Law of 1965, which featured a moratorium on designations in specific areas, and a provision to "designate or demolish" within 90 days.
  - New York Committee for a Balanced Building Boom, 1979; 224202 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 4)
    Correspondence, press releases, and newspaper clippings on the New York Committee for a Balanced Building Boom, formed to "retain the present character, quality, scale, ambiance and appearance of... Fifth Avenue in midtown Manhattan, while... supporting the continued growth and vitality of the city."
  - New York Landmarks Conservancy [8 folders], 1981-1992; 224992 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 5-12)
    Press releases, newspaper clippings, and correspondence documenting the campaigns and programs of the New York Landmarks Conservancy, a preservation advocacy group which funds the restoration and maintenance of historic properties through grants and low-interest loans.
  - New York Public Library and Midtown Rezoning, 2012-2013; 224548 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 13)
    Documentation of opposition to the New York Public Library's "Central Library Plan," which sought to replace the main research division's stacks beneath Bryant Park with a lending library and educational spaces. This folder also includes information on the proposed rezoning of the Greater East Midtown business district, which eventually happened in 2017.
  - News Boxes, 1994-2000; 224498 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 14)
    Notes and research on corner news boxes, newsstands, and other "street furniture" in New York City.
  - Operation Rainbow, 1971-1978; 228018 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 1)
    In 1971 and 1974, Joyce Matz submitted to the New York City Parks Department her proposal for "Operation Rainbow: A Pilot Program Conceived for the Children of New York City," which aimed to bring kids into the parks "not just to play, but to learn and grow" by entrusting to schools the planting and care of gardens in designated "pilot areas" of Manhattan parks.
  - Plaza Hotel, 2005-2011; 224594 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 2)
    Notes, research, press releases, and some correspondence surrounding the 2005 landmark designation of the Plaza Hotel Interior, and proposed alterations to the same.
  - Poe & Judson Houses [2 folders], 2000; 224507 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 3-4)
    Documentation of efforts to block New York University School of Law from demolishing 85 West 3rd Street, a house occupied by writer Edgar Allan Poe in 1845-46, and the adjacent Judson House, on Thompson Street, a parish building sold to NYU by the struggling Judson Memorial Church. NYU's Furman Hall, the 11-story structure which opened on the site in 2004, incorporates the facades of the historic buildings.
  - Saint John the Divine Peace Fountain [2 folders], 1984-1985; 224996 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 5-6)
    Notes, press releases, newspaper clippings, and some correspondence regarding sculptor Greg Wyatt's unusual Peace Fountain at the Cathedral Church of St. John the Divine (1047 Amsterdam Avenue). Wyatt, the Cathedral's Artist-in-Residence, created the work to mark the 200th anniversary of the Episcopal Diocese of New York in 1985.
  - Save Our Lady Queen of Angels, 2007; 224537 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 7)
    In January 2007 the Roman Catholic Archdiocese of New York announced the closure of the Church of Our Lady Queen of Angels, housed since 1886 in a sanctuary designed by William Schickel & Company at 228 East 113th Street in East Harlem. Joyce Matz provided publicity for parishioners who fought to keep the church open, and lobbied for its landmark status. Neither came to pass.
  - Save the Beacon Theatre Committee [folders 1-8 of 14], 1986-1989; 224975 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 8-15)
    A 1987 plan to convert the Beacon Theatre (2124 Broadway) to a discotheque raised an outcry from preservationists, who argued successfully in court that the alterations would damage irreparably the landmarked interior.
  - Save the Beacon Theatre Committee [folders 9-14 of 14], 1986-1989; 228373 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 1-6)
  - Save the Cottages and Garden [folders 1-7 of 28], 1997-1999; 224980 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 7-13)
    Notes, research, reports, testimony, press releases, and newspaper clippings documenting the unsuccessful fight to preserve the Cottages and Garden, a 1937 enclave of eight apartments that opened onto a private midblock green space and tennis court behind a Third Avenue commercial building. The complex, designed by architect Edward H. Faile on a site between East 77th and 78th Streets, failed to win landmark designation, and has since been replaced by a condominium tower.
  - Save the Cottages and Garden [folders 8-27 of 28], 1997-1999; 228374 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 1-20)
  - Save the Cottages and Garden [folder 28 of 28], 1997-1999; 228375 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 1)
  - Seventh Regiment Armory, 2005-2006; 228008 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 2)
    Documentation of the Empire State Development Corporation's plans to take over, restore, and renovate the Seventh Regiment Armory (a.k.a., the Park Avenue Armory, 643 Park Avenue) for use as a cultural arts center.
  - S.O.U.L. (Save Our Universalist Landmark), 1985-1998; 224276 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 3)
    Press releases, clippings, and some correspondence documenting the formation and later activities of S.O.U.L. (Save Our Universalist Landmark), a group organized to preserve the deteriorating sanctuary of the Fourth Universalist Society at 160 Central Park West.
  - Sturman property, 1997; 224281 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 4)
    Newspaper clippings regarding Upper East Side property at the southeast corner of Third Avenue and East 86th Street owned then lost by the Sturman family in a bankruptcy auction.
  - Sutton Area Community, Inc. (SAC), 1985; 224203 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 5)
    Press releases, clippings, information, and promotional material for walking tours offered by Sutton Area Community, Inc., a civic organization founded in 1975 to improve the quality of life in the vicinity of Sutton Place.
  - Tammany Hall, 2009; 228009 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 6)
    Testimony and letters of support to the New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission for Tammany Hall (100 East 17th Street), which was not designated until 2013.
  - Tavern on the Green, 2010-2012; 228011 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 7)
    Documentation of the proposed renovation and reuse of Tavern on the Green in Central Park, which had closed in 2009.
  - Town Hall [2 folders], 1978-1980; 224545 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 8-9)
    Press releases, clippings, and other documentation of the successful effort to seek landmark designation (exterior and interior) for Town Hall, the performance space designed by McKim, Mead & White at 113-123 West 43rd Street.
  - Towers on top of landmarks, 2006-2007; 227949 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 10)
    Testimony and clippings regarding proposed towers above the Parke-Bernet Gallery (980 Madison Avenue) and the New-York Historical Society (170 Central Park West). For the Historical Society's earlier plan to build a residential tower above its building, see Matz's file on the Central Park West Preservation Committee (box 1, folder 13).
  - Tudor City Association, Inc., Historic Preservation Committee, 1985-1988; 224363 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 11)
    Press releases, newspaper clippings, and information on the successful campaign to landmark Tudor City, a residential skyscraper complex on the four blocks bounded by East 40th Street, East 43rd Street, First Avenue, and Second Avenue.
  - Upper East Side Special Security District, 1994-1995; 224360 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 12)
    The Douglas Elliman real estate company proposed creating a privately policed--but taxpayer funded--"Special Security District" (later called SAFE, for "Security Area For the Eastside") between East 59th Street, East 96th Street, Fifth Avenue, and the East River. Mayor Giuliani approved the idea, which met considerable opposition.
  - West 50s, 224538 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 13)
    Testimony, correspondence, and notes about preservation efforts on West 54th, 55th, 56th, and 57th Streets.
  - Westpride (People for Westpride, Inc.) [folders 1-4 of 22], 1987-1992; 224997 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 14-17)
    Press releases, mailings, newspaper clippings, and notes documenting the opposition by this group of Upper West Siders to Donald Trump's Television City, a complex proposed for the 60th Street Rail Yard that would have featured headquarters and television studios for NBC. (For opposition to the earlier, failed, residential plan for the site—called Lincoln West—see the folders in boxes 1–2.)
  - Westpride (People for Westpride, Inc.) [folders 5-15 of 22], 1987-1992; 228376 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 1-11)
  - Westpride (People for Westpride, Inc.) [folders 16-22 of 22], 1987-1992; 228377 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 1-7)
  - Willensky Fund Award, 2000; 227107 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 8)
    Correspondence and a few clippings proclaiming Joyce Matz one of two recipients of the Elliot Willensky Fund award for 2000. Named for the late architectural historian and coauthor of the AIA Guide to New York City, the fund, established in 1991, recognized preservation advocates who kept the landmarks movement alive. Matz received the $500 prize for her campaign to secure landmark designation for a group of townhouses on East 54th and East 55th Streets (see box 7, folders 7–12).
  - Women's City Club of New York, Inc., 1988-1991; 224272 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 9)
    Correspondence, press releases, and newspaper clippings documenting the zoning reform project of the Women's City Club of New York. In conjunction with the Natural Resources Defense Council, the club released a report titled "New York City Zoning: The Need for Reform."
  - Wood, Anthony: Preserving New York, 2007; 224536 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 10)
    Draft of a press release, notes, and some correspondence surrounding the release of the book Preserving New York: Winning the Right to Protect a City's Landmarks (New York: Routledge, 2008), by preservation activist Anthony C. Wood. The New-York Historical Society Library holds a copy under call number F128.37 .W66 2008.
  - Yorkville Clock, 1998-2001; 224512 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 11)
    Efforts to restore and reinstall this sidewalk clock, a designated New York City landmark at 1501 Third Avenue.
- Series II. Public Relations, 1969-2009; 224600; 4 Linear feet
  Public relations materials (e.g., press releases, news clippings, tear sheets, correspondence, and notes) for the various organizations, businesses, individuals, and political figures promoted by Joyce Matz, first in partnership with her husband (as Mortimer Matz Associates), then eponymously (as Joyce Matz Associates), for the period 1969-2009. See descriptions at the folder level.
  Series II is sorted alphabetically by person, business, or organization name. The sheer number of newspaper clippings saved by Matz to document her work prohibited the archivist from arranging material in strictly chronological order. The researcher should, therefore, consult every folder listed under the same topic to catch items that may be out of place.
  - Acrison, Inc., 1986; 224190 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 12)
    Press releases and clippings for a Moonachie, New Jersey-based manufacturer and innovator of bulk solid processing equipment.
  - Armenian Church of America [5 folders], 1985-1989; 224400 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 13-17)
    Press releases and clippings documenting the activities of the Armenian Church of America, particularly its role in organizing the anniversary commemorations of the Armenian Genocide of 24 April 1915. (See also box 18, folders 10-18, and box 19, folders 1-11.)
  - Armenian Church of America | Armenian Earthquake, 1988; 224375 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 1)
    Press releases, clippings, and manuscript notes documenting the response of the Diocese of the Armenian Church of America to the 6.8 magnitude earthquake of 7 December 1988 that killed between 25,000 and 50,000 people in the northern region of Armenia (then part of the Soviet Union).
  - Armenian Church of America | Armenian Home for the Aged, 1983-1985; 224748 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 2)
    Press releases, clippings, and publicity materials for the church-run Armenian Home for the Aged (now called the New York Armenian Home) in Flushing, Queens. Includes Matz's bills for public relations consultation for the period February-October 1984.
  - Armenian Church of America | One World Festival [7 folders], 1980-1985; 224172 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 3-9)
    Press releases and clippings for the 8th (1980), 9th (1981), 10th (1982), 11th (1983), 12th (1984), and 13th (1985) One World Festival, co-sponsored by the Diocese of the Armenian Church of American and the Mayor's Office of Special Events, City of New York.
  - Armenian Genocide anniversary commemorations [9 folders], 1985-1988; 228534 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 10-18)
    Press releases and clippings for the 70th (1985), 71st (1986), 72nd (1987), and 73rd (1988) anniversary commemorations in New York City of the Armenian Genocide of 1914-1923, conventionally held to have started on 24 April 1915.
  - Armenian Genocide anniversary commemorations [11 folders], 1989-2000; 228538 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 1-11)
    Press releases and clippings for the 74th (1989), 75th (1990), 80th (1995), 83rd (1998), and 85th (2000) anniversary commemorations in New York City of the Armenian Genocide of 1914-1923, conventionally held to have started on 24 April 1915.
  - Biaggi, Mario, 1971-1975; 224197 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 12)